Guide to the Al cantío de un gallo Radio Program Audio Recordings
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Tape 249, 1997 March 25; 1 (Box 249)
  Side B: Había pueblos del mundo comunista que no se rebelaron. Se hace una revisión histórica de todas las rebeliones y revoluciones por las que ha pasado Cuba. Consideran que la revolución vendió Cuba a una potencia extranjera. La esclavitud del pueblo cubano es peor que la esclavitud colonial. Creen que Cuba está al borde de un estallido y del abismo ya que la destrucción del país es muy grande. Afirman que Raúl Castro es un homosexual, cirrótico y alcohólico. Consideran que el pueblo de Cuba se encuentra en una encrucijada y que el sistema no dejó sucesores, ya que se creó alrededor de un caudillo. Piensan que los cubanos se tienen que olvidar del embargo y concentrarse en buscar su libertad y el progreso de Cuba.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 250, 1997 March 25; 1 (Box 250)
  Duplicate of Tape 249 / Copia de Tape 249.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 251, 1997 March 27; 1 (Box 251)
  Side A: Alfredo Melero, Carlos Franqui. The third edition of Carta de Cuba. Franqui and Melero have recently published the third edition of Carta de Cuba, a magazine that contains chronicles, articles and poems written by independent journalists in Cuba. At the recent reunion of the CID, Franqui and Melero played recordings by Néstor Baguer, Lázaro Collazo and Héctor Peraza, all independent journalists from Cuba. In the recordings, the journalists talk about the importance of free speech, its role in a democracy, and the Cuban campaign against the free press movement. After listening to the recordings, Franqui reads a note called "The independent journalists and the Pope's visit" from their newly-published magazine. Franqui and Melero continue reading portions of the third edition of Carta de Cuba. Melero reads "Corruption and other demons," an article by Ulises Cabrera. Franqui comments on the article and talks about the roots and history of corruption in Cuba under Castro.
  Side B: Alfredo Melero, Carlos Franqui. The transition to democracy. Melero asks Franqui to talk about what he hopes for Cuba's future. Franqui replies that Cuba's struggle should be aimed toward a smooth transition to a true democracy, and that this transition should be free of anarchy and capricious justice. The dignity of the Cuban people, brought down by decades of authoritarianism, will need to be revived.
  Side A: Alfredo Melero, Carlos Franqui. El tercer número de Carta de Cuba. Franqui y Melero han recientemente publicado el tercer número de Carta de Cuba, una revista que contiene crónicas, noticias, y poemas escritas por periodistas independientes en Cuba. En la reunión reciente del CID, se escucharon grabaciones hechas por Néstor Baguer, Lázaro Collazo y Héctor Peraza, periodistas independientes de Cuba. En las tres grabaciones, los periodistas hablan sobre la importancia de la libertad de la expresión y su papel en la democracia, y la campaña del gobierno cubano contra la prensa independiente. Después de escuchar estas tres grabaciones, Melero y Franqui leen una nota del número recién salido, "Los periodistas independientes y la visita del Papa." Franqui y Melero continúan leyendo fragmentos del tercer número de Carta de Cuba. Melero lee "Corrupción y otros demonios," un artículo por Ulises Cabrera. Franqui comenta el artículo y habla sobre las raíces y la historia de la corrupción en Cuba bajo Castro.
  Side B: Alfredo Melero, Carlos Franqui. La transición a la democracia. Melero pide que Franqui hable sobre sus deseos para el futuro de Cuba. Franqui dice que la lucha cubana debería ser por una democracia verdadera y que, cuando suceda esta transición del castrismo a la democracia, no se podrá permitir ni la anarquía ni la justicia caprichosa. La dignidad del cubano, destruida después de tantos años del castrismo, tendrá que ser reconstruida.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 252, 1997 April 14; 1 (Box 252)
  Side A: Alfredo Melero, Carlos Franqui. 1. Franqui reads an article by Ulises Cabrera about an upcoming series of restrictive measures against self-employed workers in Cuba. He continues with another piece of news: the director and sub-director of "Agencia Patria," an organization of independent journalists in Cuba, have finally been found after fleeing with their families from Cuba via life rafts. Some have reached a key close to Florida; the director, however, finds himself on the Guantanamo base, about to be deported to Bolivia. Franqui finds it inexcusable that the U.S. government is unwilling to help a Cuban journalist despite receiving help from independen journalists itself. In response, Melero and Franqui are willing to mobilize the international community to condemn the U.S.'s actions. 2. Franqui and Melero speculate on rumors that the government is planning a crackdown on independent journalists and other dissidents starting on the April 15th. This move, intended to strike fear in the opposition, is yet another example of the regime's intolerance and willingness to repress. Franqui encourages the Cuban people to stand up to this kind of oppression; small acts of defiance, added together, can impede the government's operations. The speakers lament the current state of Cuba.
  Side B: Luis Zúñiga and the United Nations Commission of Human Rights. Alfredo Melero, Joaquim Torres Álvarez. Melero calls Joaquim Torres Álvarez, an independent journalist in Cuba. Joaquim reads an op-ed piece written by María Amelia Banes about Luis Zúñiga, a Cuban exile who has been included in the Nicaraguan delegation for the United Nations' Human Rights Commission gathering in Geneva.
  Side A: Alfredo Melero, Carlos Franqui. 1. Franqui lee un artículo escrito por Ulises Cabrera sobre una serie de medidas restrictivas que van a ser aplicadas a los trabajadores autónomos, medidas que harán la existencia del trabajador independiente más difícil. Franqui prosigue con otra noticia: la semana pasada, el director y la subdirectora de la Agencia Patria, una agencia de periodistas independientes, se huyeron de Cuba con sus familias en balsas. Unos llegaron a una isla cercana a la Florida; el director se encuentra en la base militar de Guantánamo, donde está bajo investigación antes de ser deportado a Bolivia. Franqui cree que es imperdonable que el gobierno de los Estados Unidos -- que cuenta con la ayuda de periodistas independientes -- no pueda ayudar al director. Como consecuencia, Franqui y Melero protestarán el gobierno de los Estados Unidos y movilizarán la comunidad internacional a condenar las acciones de EEUU. 2. Franqui y Melero hablan sobre los anuncios que a partir del día 15 de abril habría un intento de mayor represión contra la oposición y los periodistas independientes en Cuba. Este "golpe de terror" a la oposición es otro ejemplo de la inflexibilidad del gobierno y los métodos inmorales que Castro emplea para mantenerse en poder. Franqui pide que la gente de Cuba a desafié a Castro y sus exigencias – los pequeños actos de desafío, agregados, pueden impedir al gobierno. Los interlocutores lamentan el estado presente de Cuba.
  Side B: Alfredo Melero, Joaquim Torres Álvarez. "Luis Zúñiga, cubano, extranjero en su país y fuera de este." Melero llama a Joaquim Torres Álvarez, un periodista independiente en Cuba. Joaquim lee un comentario escrito por la Licenciada María Amelia Banes sobre Luis Zúñiga, un exiliado cubano que se ha unido a la delegación nicaragüense para las sesiones de la Comisión de Derechos Humanos de la ONU en Ginebra.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 253, 1997 April 14; 1 (Box 253)
  Side A: 1. The speakers commemorate two Cuban sculptors that died in exile: López Ruy [possible error in the name] and Alfredo Lozano. They narrate Lozano's life and discuss how difficult it is for an artist to work in exile and communicate with a foreign public. They also read two letters between Lozano and the poet José Lezama Lima. Franqui remembers various comments that Castro had made regarding Lezama Lima's work. 2. Franqui and Melero continue to talk about exiled Cuban artists, specifically about the location of various works of art. Franqui points out the Museo Nacional and the Iglesia del Espiritu Santo in Havana. He then returns to the letter of Lezama Lima (see part one) and remembers his earlier years when he met many artists in Cuba: Julián Orbón, Ernesto el Cubano, Carlos Montenero, Reinaldo Arenas, Severo Sarduy, Ernesto Almendro, Lidia Cabrera, Guillermo Cabrera Infante, among others.
  Side B: The speakers give recognition to the work of the independent journalists in Cuba. They discuss the effect of the Anti-Helms Burton Law (the Cuban government's reaction to the Helms Burton Act), which targets journalists even more. Castro looks for any reason to strike against them. The journalists live in terrible conditions, as they must live in hiding and do not receive pay for their work. Franqui calls on the people to help the journalists as much as they can. The Cuban population must defend its dignity, even against the United States (US), which violates Cuba's authority with its base in Guantanamo.
  Side A: 1. Los interlocutores conmemoran las muertes de dos escultores cubanos que terminaron en el exilio: López Ruy (posible equivocación en el nombre) y Alfredo Lozano. Narran la vida de Lozano y aprecian lo difícil que es trabajar en el exilio y comunicarse con un público extranjero. También se leen dos cartas intercambiadas entre Lozano y el poeta José Lezama Lima. Franqui recuerda varios comentarios de Castro a la obra de Lezama Lima. 2. Franqui y Melero siguen hablando de los artistas exiliados, específicamente de la ubicación de varias obras de Lozano en la isla. Franqui destaca el Museo Nacional y la Iglesia del Espiritu Santo en La Habana. Luego vuelve a hablar de la carta de Lezama Lima (de la primera parte del programa) y recuerda sus años tiernos cuando conocía a muchos artistas cubanos: Julián Orbón, Ernesto el Cubano, Carlos Montenero, Reinaldo Arenas, Severo Sarduy, Ernesto Almendro, Lidia Cabrera, Guillermo Cabrera Infante, y otros.
  Side B: Los interlocutores aprecian el trabajo de los periodistas independientes en Cuba. Tratan el efecto de la Ley Anti-Helms Burton (la reacción por parte del gobierno cubano a la Ley Helms Burton) que se les hace aún más difícil a los periodistas. Castro busca cualquier pretexto para darles un golpe. Los periodistas viven en condiciones terribles, ya que tienen que esconderse y no reciben dinero por su trabajo. Franqui pide que el pueblo ayude a estos periodistas personalmente. El pueblo cubano tiene que defender su dignidad, aun ante los Estados Unidos, quien ofende a Cuba con su base en Guantánamo.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 254, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 254)
  Side A: 1. Cuba is losing nearly all its natural resources because the government is selling them off to foreign countries. The tobacco industry, for example, now belongs to Spain. This is part of a long line of abuses inflicted by Castro on the country, from his relationship with the Soviet Union to the recent laws that favor tourism over local commerce. It is time that each Cuban citizen begins to think of ways to personally take revenge against Castro's regime. 2. Franqui and Melero discuss the mass emigrations from Cuba to Miami. When Castro came to power, Cuba's relationship with the US greatly improved for having overthrown Batista. Castro destroyed any chance of a cooperative relationship with the US when he made Cuba a communist country. When Cuban people flee to the US, they realize how wealthy the country is, which further promotes the desire to leave Cuba. The US no longer wants to take in any immigrants, and Franqui proposes that this can serve as a basis for the opposition to gain American support.
  Side B: Franqui compares the current situation in Cuba to the times when the people fought for its independence from Spain. He also talks about how to protect Cuba's culture from North American influence, as Puerto Rico has done. [There are moments when the recording is inaudible.]
  Side A: 1. Cuba está perdiendo casi todos sus recursos naturales porque se los vende a países extranjeros. El tabaco, por ejemplo, se le ha vendido a España. Esto forma parte de una larga tradición de abusos que Castro ha infligido al país, desde su relación con la Unión Soviética hasta las leyes que favorecen el turismo sobre el comercio local. Es hora de que cada cubano empiece a pensar en su desquite personal contra el régimen. 2. Franqui y Melero hablan de las grandes emigraciones de gente de Cuba hacia Miami. Cuando Castro subió al poder, la relación entre Cuba y los Estados Unidos se mejoró bastante por haber derribado a Batista. Castro liquidó la posibilidad de mantener amistad con los EEUU cuando hizo de Cuba un país comunista. Cuando los cubanos que huyen se dan cuento de cuán rico es EEUU, se propaga el deseo de salir de la isla. Hoy EEUU no quiere más inmigrantes, y Franqui propone que a base de esto la oposición cubana busque apoyo del gobierno norteamericano.
  Side B: Franqui compara la situación actual en Cuba a los tiempos en que el pueblo luchaba por su independencia de España. Tambien habla de la posibilidad de mantener la cultura cubana ante la influencia norteamericana, como ha hecho Puerto Rico. [Hay momentos en que no se puede escuchar la grabación.]
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 255, 1997 April 29; 1 (Box 255)
  Side A: 1. Joaquín Torre Álvarez reads several reports about the recent activities of the group Havana PRE. He then talks with Melero about the possibility of a future reconciliation with the United States (US), during the presidency of Bill Clinton. There are several minutes of background noise with no content. 2. Melero talks to Lázaro Lazo about the sale of Cuba's natural resources to foreign countries and about this year's sugarcane harvest. 3. Melero reports the news to Franqui. 4. Melero calls Raúl Ribero to discuss the news. Near the end are nearly four minutes without content. Then Melero speaks briefly with an unnamed person.
  Side B: Melero invites Lázaro Lazo to describe recent events in Cuba. Lazo talks about the oppressive nature of the police, contraband, the poverty in the neighborhoods of Havana and the food rations. There was a large protest in Havana that displayed the high levels of tension in the city. Melero introduces Rodolfo Silva, who speaks with Lazo about the importance of the press in Cuba. There are several minutes with only background noise.
  Side A: 1. Joaquín Torre Álvarez lee varios informes sobre las actividades recientes del grupo Habana-PRE. Luego habla con Melero sobre la posibilidad de una reconciliación futura con Estados Unidos, durante la presidencia de Bill Clinton. Hay varios minutos sin contenido. 2. Melero y Lázaro Lazo hablan de la venta de los recursos naturales de Cuba al extranjero, de la cosecha de zafra de este añoy de la explosión en el Hotel Coiba en La Habana. 3. Melero pasa las noticias a Franqui. 4. Melero llama a Raúl Ribero para hablar de las noticias. Al final quedan casi cuatro minutes sin contenido, y luego una breve conversación entre Melero y un individuo innominado.
  Side B: Melero invita a Lázaro Lazo a relatar los sucesos actuales de la isla de Cuba. Lazo habla del carácter opresivo de la policía, el contrabando, la miseria en los barrios de La Habana y las raciones de comestibles. Hubo una gran protesta en La Habana donde se manifestó toda la tensión de la ciudad. Melero presenta a Rodolfo Silva, quien habla con Lazo del trabajo de los periodistas en Cuba. Hay varios minutos sin contenido.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 256, 1996; 1 (Box 256)
  Side A: 1. Melero speaks on the phone with Blas Ramiro, who reports on a press conference where he presented a forthcoming bulletin that will focus on a socioeconomic analysis of the situation in Cuba. The theme of the first issue will be the elections and obligatory voting in the country. Ramiro hopes that this bulletin will show non-violent defiance to the government. In his opinion, Cuba's biggest problem is not its relationship with the United States, but with its own people. 2. Melero speaks with Lázaro Lazo, who reports on the sugarcane harvest, which has been the worst one in the past fifty years, and its disastrous effects on the Cuban economy. Although the government claims the economy is growing, it is obviously crashing. The government is mistreating the Cuban laborers. After, Lazo describes the celebrations of the First of May. 3. Melero interviews Catalina Mayoral, a member of Madres y Mujeres Anti-Represión (M.A.R.), a group that fights for the civil rights of the Cuban people. Recently the group has taken on the case of Dr. Leonel Morejón Almagro, who has been in prison since February 15, 1996, and who has been nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize. 4. There is a brief conversation between Melero and Tony Santiago; they make plans to call each other back.
  Side B: 1. Franqui compares the situation in Cuba to Pandora's box; he says the Cuban people fell in love with the beauty of the Revolution, but when they embraced it all the evils of the world were unleashed. The sugarcane harvest this year has not even reached three million tons. Ramón Castro has become the country's general latifundista (estate owner). The Cuban farmer receives so little money that he cannot even afford shoes to wear when he works. The two speakers agree that Castro must be removed from Cuba. 2. Melero speaks about the farce of elections in Cuba, since the winning candidate is known from the beginning. Franqui talks about the journalists that fight for the rights of the people; he also talks about the plight of the farmers and the political prisoners (including Dr. Leonel Morajón Almagro). He says that the Cuban people are too passive in their resistance. Castro has made Cuba a third-world country where the capital city does not even have transportation. Castro has turned over the country's richest resources to foreign powers: sugar, coffee, rum, nickel, and its beaches and hotels. Neither the embargo, nor the Helms Burton Act nor the European Union can remedy the situation; it is the responsibility of the Cuban people. 3. Repetition of the interview with Catalina Mayoral (see Side A).
  Side A: Melero habla con Blas Ramiro por teléfono, quien da un reportaje sobre una conferencia de prensa donde se presentó un boletín cuyo propósito es el análisis socioeconómico de la situación en Cuba. El tema del primer número va a ser las elecciones y la votación obligatoria en la isla. Ramiro espero que este boletín sea un desafío al gobierno y una muestra de la lucha pacífica. A su parecer, el gran problema del país no es entre Cuba y los Estados Unidos, sino entre Cuba y su propia gente. Segunda parte: Melero habla con Lázaro Lazo, quien informa sobre la cosecha de zafra, que ha sido la peor de los últimos cincuenta años en la isla, y sus efectos desastrosos para la economía cubana. Aunque el gobierno ha dicho que crecerá la economía, se ve que va para abajo. Además, el gobierno maltrata al obrero cubano. Luego Lazo describe las celebraciones del primero de mayo. Tercera parte: Melero entrevista a Catalina Mayoral, miembro de Madres y Mujeres Anti-Represión (M.A.R.), un grupo que aboga por los derechos civiles de la gente cubana. Últimamente este grupo está abogando por el doctor Leonel Morejón Almagro, quien ha guardado prisión desde el 15 de febrero de 1996 y ha sido nominado al Premio Nobel de la Paz. Cuarta parte: Hay una breve conversación entre Melero y Tony Santiago; hacen planes de volver a llamarse.
  Side B: 1. Franqui compara la situación en Cuba con la caja de Pandora; dice que el pueblo cubano se enamoró de la belleza de la Revolución, pero al alcanzarla se soltaron todos los malos del mundo. La zafra este año ni ha llegado a la cifra de tres millones de toneladas. Ramón Castro se ha convertido en latifundista de toda la isla. El agricultor cubano recibe tan poco dinero que ni tiene zapatos para ponerse cuando va a cortar caña. Los dos interlocutores quedan en que Castro tiene que irse de Cuba. 2. Melero habla de la farsa de las elecciones en Cuba, ya que el candidato ganador está elegido desde antes. Franqui habla de los periodistas que están luchando por los derechos del pueblo, de los agricultores y de los presos políticos (entre ellos el doctor Leonel Morajón Almagro). Dice que la gente cubana es demasiado pasiva en su resistencia. Castro ha convertido Cuba en un tercer mundo donde ni hay transporte por la ciudad. Castro les ha entregado a los extranjeros lo mejor del país: el azúcar, el café, el ron, el níquel, las playas y los hoteles. Ni el embargo, ni la Ley Helms Burton ni la Unión Europea pueden ayudar; la responsabilidad queda en las manos del pueblo cubano. 3. Repetición de la entrevista con Catalina Mayoral (Side A).
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 257, 1997; 1 (Box 257)
  Side A: 1. The result of communism is that it develops a totalitarian system in the country. Franqui sees that the Cuban people are united, and he believes this will help the opposition to mobilize them against Castro. However, the Cuban people must stop fleeing the country in clandestine boats. Castro treats the citizens like slaves. As Castro ages and suffers from illnesses, he takes out his frustration on the people. Havana used to be one of the most dynamic cities in the world, now it is one of the poorest. 2. Franqui and Melero continue to emphasize the breakdown of Cuba under Castro. Franqui defends his participation in the Revolution: the revolution he participated in had promised justice for all and support for the peasants. Melero reminds us that everyone supported the Revolution because it promised great things. The reality, however, is that Castro has prostituted the country and the people now live worse than animals. They stress that the Cuban people are responsible for removing Castro.
  Side A: 1. El logro del comunismo es que desarrolla un sistema totalitario. Franqui ve que el pueblo cubano es muy unido, y por eso cree que la oposición puede movilizar al país a reaccionar contra Castro. Sin embargo, primero la gente cubana debe dejar de lanzarse al mar para huir del país. Castro trata al pueblo cubano como a esclavos. Castro tiene una rabia por su vejez y su enfermedad, y se desahoga por perseguir y fastidiar a todo el mundo. Antes La Habana era una de las ciudades más dinámicas del mundo, ahora es una de las más miserables. 2. Franqui y Melero siguen destacando el desmoronamiento de Cuba bajo Castro. Franqui defiende su participación en la Revolución: la revolución en que participó prometía justicia a todos los ciudadanos y apoyo a los campesinos. Melero hace acordar que todos apoyaron la Revolución porque se prometía mucho. La realidad, sin embargo, es que Castro ha prostituido al país y la gente vive en peores condiciones que los animales. Recalcan que el pueblo cubano es responsable de echar a Castro.
  - Preservation master, 1
  - Use copy, 1
- Tape 258, Circa 1997; 1 (Box 258)